#大家好 現在秋天啦
Hi everyone! It's autumn now.
#我們上山的那個拐棗也熟了哦
Our oriental raisins on the hill are ready,
#也熟啦
ready now.
#就在那邊
Just over there.
#走上去
Let's go!
#哇 這個玉米地
Wa! The corn field...
#擋路
It blocks my way.
#誒 這裡有一棵小棵的
Eh! Here's a small tree,
#好小啊
a very small tree.
#你看 這個
Look! This is,
#這個 我們這邊的方言叫作
this is, in our dialect here, it's called,
#(註︰原字幕沒有，但我想應該是「金鈎梨」)
"jin nou le"
#它拐來拐去的
It's bending here and there.
#所以叫拐棗
So it's called "guai zau" (lit: bending date)
#嗯
Um!
#還有一點澀
It's still a bit chalky.
#不過沒有關係
But never mind,
#澀也可以吃
chalkiness doesn't do any harm.
#嗯
Um!
#哇 這裡有個大的
Wa! Here's a large one.
#這個比較肥
This is fatter.
#嗯 這個稍微大一點就比較甜一點
Um! This is, larger and it tastes sweeter.
#你看 這個
Look! This is,
#可能樹上掉下來 剛好被這個葉子掛住啦
perhaps it fell from the tree and landed right onto the leaf.
#這個
This one,
#這個也還好吃
it tastes not too bad.
#哇 有點澀
Wa! It's a bit chalky.
#我們檢多一點回去
Let's pick more,
#用來泡酒
to infuse our liquor.
#這毎 聽老人家說啊
You know, the elderly say,
#這個 拐棗
that, the oriental raisin,
#拐棗
oriental raisin,
#泡酒
is good for health,
#很補的哦
when soaked with wine.
#我也沒喝過那個酒
I've never tried this kind of wine.
#回家試一下
Now I have the chance.
#你看 就檢了那麼一點也好
Look! Just a bit here is already not too bad.
#我們去那
Let's go there,
#那邊一棵樹上再檢一點
another tree there, to pick a bit more.
#看有沒有啦
Let's see if there are any.
#哎喲 有玉米喲
Ayo! Corns!
#摘點玉米回去餵豬
Let's pick some corns for the pigs.
#那豬沒 沒東西吃啦
We have no, no more food for the pigs.
#哎喲 把這個放著先
Ayo! Put it here first.
#你看 這裡有兩個哦
Look! Here are two,
#雙胞胎
twins.
#這個是沒甚麼肉的哦 這個
There are hardly any kernels.
#但是豬很喜歡吃這種
But the pigs like it very much.
#掰開來看一下
Let's take a look inside.
#哇 這個
Wa! This is,
#這是它芯
this is the cob.
#這條芯豬是很喜歡吃的
The cob is the pigs' favourite.
#拿回去給豬吃
Take it back for the pigs.
#嗯 這裡有一個
Um! Here's one,
#也有一個
and another one.
#這個 應該有點肉吧
There, should be some kernels, I think.
#耶 沒肉
Yea, nothing.
#沒肉也 也帶回去
I don't care. I'll take it.
#哇 這裡有兩個
Wa! Here are two.
#這個肯定有肉啦
They must have some kernels.
#你看 這裡有一個大的哦
Look! Here's a large one.
#摘大的 聲音都不一樣
The size makes a difference. Listen to the sound!
#看一下有沒有肉
Let's have a look inside.
#哎呀 有一坨肉
Aya! I can see some kernels.
#可以
Not bad!
#一個小的 小的也把它摘掉
Here's a small one. I am taking it anyway.
#就摘了那麼一點點
So I've picked just, a bit.
#我去
Let me continue,
#另外一個地方摘
at another place.
#這些還不夠小豬吃一頓
That's not enough even for a single meal.
#哎呀 有點重哦
Aya! It's a bit heavy.
#額 到了另外一棵樹哦
Ah! So we arrive at another tree.
#樹上都沒有啦
But there's nothing in the tree.
#全部掉下來啦
The fruits have all fallen down,
#掉下在地方
onto the ground.
#哇 這裡有一個
Wa! Here's one.
#很靚的哦 這個
It's beautiful.
#你看
Look!
#很結實
It's hard and firm.
#好少啊
It's too few.
#這邊有一個
One here.
#就檢了那麼一點點
So we have just a bit here.
#我們拿回去泡酒
Let's soak them with the wine.
#這個還有一點澀 不好吃
It doesn't taste good. It's still a bit chalky.
#用來泡
Soak it,
#泡我們的料酒
soak with our cooking wine.
#現在把這個拐棗剪一下
Now I'll cut the oriental raisins,
#剪得漂漂亮亮的來
cut them prettily.
#你看 就這樣一塊肉一塊肉把它剪下來
Look! I'm just cutting it into pieces.
#要把這個籽剪掉
The seed needs to be cut away.
#我們再來
Again...
#你看 小狗
Look! The puppies are,
#睡
having,
#睡得那麼香啊 狗狗
having sweet dreams, puppies.
#睡得像豬一樣
They're sleeping like a pig.
#把這個拐棗洗一下
Let me wash them.
#那些 你看
Well, look!
#還有籽都掉下去啦
The remaining seeds are being washed away.
#那籽不要 淨起來的這個籽都不要
Discard them, the floating seeds too.
#我們再把它曬乾
We'll then dry them under the sun.
#曬乾之後
After drying,
#就放
we'll pour,
#放點酒去泡它
pour some wine onto it.
#把這個拐棘曬一下 曬乾來
Now I put the oriental raisins under the sun, to dry them.
#這一個樹枝
Here's a branch.
#曬個半個小時 應該全部都乾啦
They will all be dried in half an hour.
#現在天氣那麼乾燥
It's so dry these days.
#把這個玉米 背上去餵豬
I'm now taking the corns to feed the pigs.
#小豬都帶娃
The piggy is taking care of the babies.
#好多哇
It has a lot of babies,
#帶了七八條 (註︰明明只有七隻小狗，何來第八隻？)
seven or eight puppies.
#現在曬乾啦 我把它放到這個罐子上去
So now it's dried. Put it into this jar.
#肯定很好吃
It must be very tasty.
#這個泡酒很香的哦
It smells really good with the wine.
#現在都聞得到香味啦
I can smell it now.
#再加上酒
So the wine.
#很靚的哦 你看
It's beautiful! Look!
#顏色還那麼的深下來啦
The color darkens immediately.
#好大的酒味呀 這個
It smells too strong.
#蓋起來
Seal it.
#下次有粉絲過來
Next time when our fans come to visit us,
#拿出來
we can,
#一起分享
share with them,
share with them.
#好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
#放著 珍藏版
Keep it well! Limited edition.